[MUSIC]
[訪問丹尼爾.賽門斯]
So we're here in the office with Dan
Simons, someone you might have heard of
今天我們訪問丹尼爾.西蒙斯(Dan Simons)
because in many introduction to psychology
lectures there's this video of a gorilla
你應該在心理學課程中看過有隻大猩猩在一群人中遊走，
卻沒有人發現的影片
walking through a group of people and
people don't notice this gorilla.
你應該在心理學課程中看過有隻大猩猩在一群人中遊走，
卻沒有人發現的影片
You might have even read this book and
也許你已經讀過他寫的科普書
(The Invisible Gorilla)
if you haven't then I
highly recommend you do.
沒有的話，強烈建議你找來看看
Where he describes this type of research.
書中描述相當多類似的研究
But this is not what I'm going to talk
about today because then Simons is also,
不過這並不是我們今天要討論的主題
together with Alex Holcomb and
丹尼爾.西蒙斯與Alex Holcomb
Jennifer Tackett, an editor at
Perspectives on Psychological Science.
以及Perspective of Psychological Science的編輯Jennifer Tackett
Where they have this new article format.
一起架構「註冊再現研究」的發表格式
So Dan, there's this new type
of research just published it's
那麼，丹，我們來談談什麼是「註冊再現研究」
known as a registered replication report.
Yes.
好的
And people do research but
這種發表方式和一般科學論文發表的方式有點不同
it's a little bit different
than a normal journal paper.
這種發表方式和一般科學論文發表的方式有點不同
Yeah, it's very much different
than a normal journal article.
是的，這與一般的期刊論文相當不同
So, in a normal journal article
people will run their one or
一般的論文發表，研究者通常做一個
two studies or three studies,
they'll compile them into a package and
到三個研究，再統整結果
then they'll submit that as a publication.
投稿到期刊發表
What a register replication report is
designed to do is to estimate the size and
「註冊再現研究」的設計著重估計重要發現的效果量，穩健度，信度，以及一致性
the robustness and reliability and
consistency of an important finding.
「註冊再現研究」的設計著重估計重要發現的效果量，穩健度，信度，以及一致性
So what we do is we
find a finding that all
所以我們選出一些已經公開發表的研究
ready been published in the Literature.
One that has been cited many times or
而這些研究都已經被其他文獻大量引用
talked about in the media that is really
influential in the field or in the public,
或是在媒體上被大量的討論，且對該領域有著相當程度的影響
and we design a protocol to
directly replicate that study.
我們設計一種直接複製該項研究協定範本
So to do the same thing again.
也就是再做一次原始研究的細節
And we take that design, build out
the protocol, write out the scripts.
我們根據原始研究擬定協定，編撰程序腳本
And then we put out a call for other labs
that want to join in this project, and
然後廣邀有興趣的實驗室參加這個專案
they each will then replicate the original
study using exactly the same protocol.
所有參加的實驗室根據協定再現原始研究
So we have anywhere from 10 to 30 labs
一個專案可能會有10到30個實驗室參與
conducting the same study in the same way
across the wide range of cultures and
在不同的文化與受試者母群
across the wide range
of subject populations.
用同樣的方式複製原始研究的細節
What that allows to do is to say,
how consistent to this effect?
這樣的方式可以評估原始實驗效果的一致性
We basically combine all the results in
a meta analysis that allows us to say,
我們使用整合分析(meta analysis)分析所有實驗室的結果
what's the overall average effect for
this original study,
估計原始研究的整體平均效果量
and how variable is it
across all of these labs.
以及參與實驗室之間的變異
So it sounds like the article's
almost already written
這麼聽起來，好像是論文一開始就已經寫好了
with this protocol perspective,
there's already a lot of stuff.
以研究設計協定的部分來說
該有的都已經有了
And then you just go and collect the data?
而你們只是去取得更多的實驗數據?
Essentially, yeah.
基本上沒錯
So, when we design this, we have the study
already designed, we can, in principle,
當我們設計時，因為我們已經有原始研究的設計
可以把整份論文手稿先寫好
write the entire manuscript in advance
because we know what the theory is,
因為我們已經知道理論是什麼
we know what the history is,
we know what the methods are.
知道研究的背景
也知道研究方法
We build out these methods, labs go and
conduct the study themselves, and
我們規劃好研究方法後
所有參與的實驗室就各自去做實驗
then they report the results
in a standardized way.
然後再以統一的形式撰寫結果報告
Okay, so why is it actually important
to publish this new type of article?
好的
那來談談這種新型態的研究論文的重要性吧
Well, one of the critical aspects of
this sort of registered replication report
最重要一點是，「註冊再現研究」可以提供傳統研究論文無法提供的訊息
is, it does something that no
other kind of article can do.
最重要一點是，「註冊再現研究」可以提供傳統研究論文無法提供的訊息
So lots of study have been published
that are then replicated by one lab
即使一間實驗室自行再現一種已被發表的實驗效果
in a single study, but
any one study can't really be definitive.
依然還不能確定這種效果真實存在
Any one study, unless it's amazingly
large, one study's almost never
除非一種研究收集成千上萬的資料
compelling evidence that withstand
all possible forms of variability,
足以涵蓋所有可能的變異性及取樣誤差
all sorts of problems of a sampling error.
否則無法成為足以令人信服的證據
So what this approach does is gives you
所以，註冊再現研究
an unbiased estimate of
how big the effect is.
可以得到無偏誤(unbiased)的實驗效果量估計值
And we only will do this for
而我們只針對那些
studies that have some doubt
about how strong the effect is.
實驗效果有存疑的研究進行複製實驗
Not that we expect them to not be there,
but there's only been one study, or
並不是因為我們不相信它
而是如果只有單一的實驗結果
it hasn't been directly replicated many
times, or there are a whole bunch of
或是那項實驗從沒有被複製過
related studies that use different
methods that suggested more things.
甚至可能一系列有相關，卻使用不同實驗方式的研究
進而出現更多不同的結論
But because only positive results
tend to get published in literature,
可是，因為通常只有顯著結果才被發表
we just don't know how reliable
these sorts of effects are.
我們很難去了解這些效應的信度
Many of the originals were done with
fairly small samples, which means we,
由於很多研究往往只取了一小群樣本
again, don't have a great idea of how
consistent and how big these effects are.
這代表我們也很難去了解該效應的一致性及效果量
So that's the broad goal.
這就是推出「註冊再現研究」的目的
It does something that no other
method can do as robustly.
這種研究結果可以達到傳統研究無法達到的穩健度
Lots of replications are great, and
single replications are really useful,
無論是大量或單一實驗都可以用這種方式再現
they provide more information.
可以提供更多傳統研究無法提供的訊息
This provides a lot more consistent
information using a vetted,
註冊再現研究依經過審定的協定進行實驗
evaluated protocol to make
sure we get it right.
能用具一致性的訊息審視實驗結果的正確性
And of course it's certain
it will appear in print.
當然，所有實驗室的結果都會被發表
Exactly so
的確
the results of every one of these studies
are combined regardless of the outcome.
無論結果顯不顯著，所有的實驗結果都會被整合
And they all get included in the paper,
so there's no publication bias,
並一起放進論文裡發表
所以不會有出版偏誤的問題
we don't have only the positive
results appearing.
我們不會總只有顯著結果
We have all results from all of
the studies and all of the participants
我們的結果來自所有參與實驗室的成員
in a single paper, and all of
the participants are authors on the paper.
全部都放在同一篇期刊論文裡發表
所有參與的實驗室成員都是論文作者
So what inspired you to become an editor and
那麼你一開始為什麼會想擔任編輯
to publish this type of article?
發表這類型的研究論文呢?
The idea for this sort of article
發表這類型論文的想法起源於
was something that my colleague Alex
Holton and I talked about many years ago.
多年前我與同事 Alex Holton 的談話
So in psychology there were a state
of prominent cases of fraud,
心理學領域裡有很多著名的學術醜聞
and that's not really directly
relevant here, the replication or
當然這與今天討論的無法再現實驗結果無關
failure to replicate a study doesn't
have anything to do with fraud.
當然這與今天討論的無法再現實驗結果無關
But the combination of those
high profile fraud cases coupled
但是把那些著名的學術醜聞
with the failure to replicate some fairly
prominent findings in the literature,
和知名卻無法被成功再現的研究結果放在一起來看
as well as a bunch of findings
appearing in the literature that
還有那些「震驚全球心理學界」的實驗結果
lots of people would look at them say,
that just can't be.
還有那些「震驚全球心理學界」的實驗結果
So we saw this as an issue of incentives.
我們覺得這是個該被解決的問題
There's a really strong incentive
to publish new novel findings, and
發表全新的實驗結果對研究者的吸引力
not as much of an incentive to make sure
that these novel findings are robust or
遠大於確定這種實驗結果的穩健度或測量的準確性
to measure them precisely.
Those incentives were lacking in the field
and one of the things we wanted to do
這些工作在心理學領域是沒人想做的
卻是我們要去做的
was to say, hey let's take these findings
that people are using in their research,
我們針對那些常被人拿來持續研究的實驗結果
that they're using to build theories,
that they're using to make public policy,
或是被架構新理論，或影響公共政策的實驗結果
let's take a look at these findings and
say, are they robust?
召集研究者仔細檢視這些發現的穩健度
And we really hope they are, but
they just hadn't been tested.
當然，我們希望已發表的研究都是穩健的結果
只是從來沒有人去測試這些結果的穩健度
So it was a need in the field.
斦以需要我們挺身而出
Okay, excellent.
非常好
Thank you very much.
謝謝你
[MUSIC]
[訪問結束]